[Music]
This is software engineering radio, the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at
se-radio.net. SE radio is brought to you
by the ITLE computer society and by it e
software magazine online at
computer.org/software.
[Music]
Hi everyone, this is Priyanka Ragwin for
software engineering radio and today on
our show we're going to be discussing
the topic stateless decoupled
authorization frameworks and for this we
have two guests Alex Olivia and Emra
Baram. Embra is an entrepreneur and a
software executive with more than 20
years of experience in B2B and B2C
product areas. He's currently the
co-founder and CEO of Serbos and before
that he co-founded Turkeykey's largest
social network in the mid 2000s called
yonja.com and after that been in a
variety of different organizations. One
is of course Google and Qbit and one of
the podcasts he appeared on they called
him a serial entrepreneur. So going to
stick with that and Alex he's the CPO
and co-founder at Serbos. He has a wide
variety of roles and experiences be an
engineer, consultant, tech lead, product
manager and there's also this one line
which says always an eye on developer
experience. So that's great for us here
at SE radio. He's worked on different
companies again Microsoft Cubit and a
myriad of startups with a focus on areas
such as authorization, data management
and security. So welcome to the show
Emra and Alex. Thank you for having us.
Yeah, great. So in SE radio we've done a
few shows on authorization as well as
authentication on episode 492 which I
just want to call out to the listeners.
We had a show on building consistent
authorization service mainly on the
Google Sabbar project that we talked
about and then episode 406 on the open
policy agent. We've done a few shows on
ooth 2 and API authorization. However,
since we are exploring this topic again,
I think nearly after a gap about four
years, can I pose this question to both
of you on what is authorization? So,
Emra, can I start with you? Sure. I want
to start by saying what it is not.
Authorization usually comes with its
twin authentication. And authentication
is a fact of who you are. Are you who
you say you are and what roles and what
attributes you have? That's
authentication and your directory. And
authorization is the fact that now we
know who you are. Are you allowed to do
a certain action or not? And you can
think about this the application of this
in many things in life as well as in
software. You know the fact that you can
log in doesn't really mean you can do
every action in any given software. And
the control mechanism of what are you
allowed to do versus not is
authorization.
Great. Yeah. And I think there's a
really good analogy for anyone that's
taken a flight recently. You got your
passport, you fly to some exotic
location for your vacation. You get to
passport control. They take your
passport. They authenticated to you by
comparing your photo and your
biometrics. It's like, cool, Alex has
arrived. This is his document. But the
actual decision of whether you're
allowed into the country or not is an
authorization decision which is based
upon, you know, have you got the right
visa? What's your immigration status?
Have you got the right funds? Those sort
of things. And that's a check. knows who
you are but should you actually be
allowed in is the difference between
authentication and authorization. That's
a great example and I think maybe Alex
I'll ask you this question then in a lot
of literature I see there's this term
called as an authorization model is that
something that you can describe for us
and maybe what are the key components
yeah so authorization authorization
models there's kind of various ways you
can think about what decides access to a
particular system and the term that I
imagine most of this audience would be
familiar with is arbback or role-based
access control where your authorization
your access is controlled by whether you
have a particular role or not. So you
must be an admin to do certain actions.
You must be a user to do other actions.
You must be a subscriber to do the
download action. Let's say artback is
one that probably most people are
familiar with. Aback or attribute based
access control is kind of the either the
evolution or the superset or the subset
depends how you look at the world of
that and that's about deciding your
access based on more than just your
role. It's about deciding access based
on attributes and those could be
attributes about who you are. It could
be attributes based upon the resource
you're accessing. It could be attributes
based on the context. So where did this
request come from? Is it from a known
IP? Those kind of rules. And there's
lots of different components you can
bring in to decide your access. There's,
you know, other models such as
relationship based access control where
your access is based upon what relations
you have with a particular entity or the
resource you're trying to access. So
there's different ways of approaching
authorization and there's use cases for
all of those and there's some cases
where doing an attribute based control
check is more sensible than doing a
relationship based or vice versa. And so
it really goes back to as always looking
at your requirements looking at your use
cases and then picking the model that's
best for your system and best for your
requirements inside of your application.
I think I'm going to come back with a
question there on that, but I think it's
a good point for me to also discuss a
little bit on why you think
authorization is important for software
engineering teams. So, Emry, I'm just
going to give it to you because I
thought it would be good for you to
explain this and maybe is there
something that you can relate to an
example where things have gone bad
because authorization was implemented
incorrectly? Yep, you can think of many
different examples, but also there are
real life examples of when authorization
goes wrong or when authorization isn't
actually taken seriously. A simple one I
can give you an example of is imagine
these neo banks, right? These neo banks
giving you a bank account that you can
actually log in and suddenly you start
using that bank account for your company
and multiple people need access to it to
be able to do certain things. But
suddenly because there is no roles and
permissions or limitations that have
been in these user accounts, everybody
is capable of making as large transfers
as they want or everybody's capable of
seeing everything. And certainly as a
software builder, you don't want that,
right? You want to make sure everybody's
limited to their roles and limitations
of what they should be able to do. If we
want to look at a disaster case
scenario, we can actually take a look at
news in early days of a very popular
right share application where people
from the customer service team or people
from inside the company who had uneed
access to everything within their thing.
They were able to take a look at some
celebrities account and the trips that
they have actually taken. You know, in a
normal world scenario, you only want to
be able to enable the right person at
the right time to be able to look into
that trip. But now everybody has access.
In the correct world implementation, a
person should only be able to take a
look at that account if there's a
complaint if there's an issue with a
payment or if there's a complaint from a
driver or from the rider. Other than
that, nobody should be able to go in and
take a look at that account. And that is
a lack of proper author thinking about
authorization and requirements and
limitations and not actually
implementing them. I think that's a case
where there's a term also the granular
control in a permission management
system. So they don't have good granular
controls is what I'm hearing. Exactly.
Probably in that scenario they had
customer success employees can take a
look at the right information. That's as
coarse as it gets. But what does that
mean? They can look at anybody's
information. They can look at any time
frame, any country and anything. So
that's coarse grained. But a fine
grained one would be only you can take a
look at a specific customer that there
is a you know support case open for or
you can take a look at only a you know
customer's again trip if you have been
specifically given permission to look at
because of an upstream event that has
happened. Okay. I think Alex based on
what Embra said you talked about the
domain model and you explained to us
like you know the Aback and RBback and
relationship based access control. So I
was wondering when you have a like an
authorization model can you have many
types of things can you have an arback
aback and also like a reback in the same
model. Yeah. So the way to kind of think
about it is less to do with whether it's
aback or arback or reback etc. It's more
about is this more of a policy based
model or is this more of a sort of a
datadriven model and what I mean by that
is policy based model which is you know
what service is is where you have
policies that define here are the
different resources here are the
different actions and here are the
conditions under which those actions
should be allowed and it could be that
simple rback role based check where you
simply say has this user got this role
or it could be a more fine grain
attribute based check where you're
looking for individual attributes about
the user and the resource they're trying
to access and that's defined as a static
versioned tested audit edited policy.
But the key thing in that model is
there's no actual user or resource data
stored in it. It's purely the rule set
and then at evaluation time the system
or the architecture would bring the data
to that rule set. That rule set will be
evaluated. The policies will be
evaluated and the simple allow or deny
decision comes back in the kind of
primary use case. The model the other
approach is kind of where the
permissions is embedded in the data
itself. You know you mentioned Zanzibar
at the start. The Zanzibar white paper
outlines the architecture behind s of
Google Drive and Google Docs. And in
that world, you're basically storing the
data. You're storing the relationships
between resources inside of this sort of
authorization layer itself. So in that
world, you don't just store the
policies, you're actually maintaining
the relationships or the permissions
between individual resources. And so
that requires you to kind of replicate
and duplicate and synchronize data into
your permission store. On the policy
based approach end, that isn't a
requirement. you bring the data to the
authorization system when you need to do
a check. That way it ensures it's always
up to date and correct and you're always
going to get the answer based on the
most relevant data. And so it's kind of
two-way approach and again it goes back
to kind of what your architecture base
most sense but being that policy driven
approach I personally think is kind of
the one that gives you the most clarity
of exactly what your rules are and you
can inspect and understand exactly
what's going to happen inside of the
system. When we did the show four years
back on building a consistent global
authorization service, we talked about
the Zanzibar project and then there was
a big question there on they had
specific goals on correctness,
flexibility, low latency, high
availability and large scale. Obviously,
it's Google but then I wanted to ask you
and I I guess this is a question I've
seen in a lot of other podcasts that
people have asked the two of you. Where
does it make sense to, you know, build
your own service like Zanzibar and where
do you use an offthe-shelf authorization
service? But I'm sorry I have to ask you
the question again. Can you give us some
advice? It's a great question. We get
asked this all the time ourselves and
the whole reason we started Serbos
nearly 4 years ago now is we've had to
build this ourselves in previous
companies. Myself both as a developer
and then laterally as a product manager,
I've been both the guy that had to write
the code and also the guy that had to
write the specification. And the
commonality there is it was never a core
functionality of the business we were
building this in. I've had to build this
for supply chain systems. I had to build
this from Rex systems. I've had to build
this for analytic system. I had to build
this for finance systems. And the common
thing is those businesses were not
authorization systems. We should have
been spending our engineering time on
delivering the features and the
capabilities that our customers actually
wanted. And much like you would never
build a database today, you would never
build file storage today. You would
never go and build an image processing
pipeline today. Those are things you can
just pull off the shelf. So, apart from,
you know, edge cases where you do need a
very specific system, we're in a world
now where there's amazing open source
projects out there where you can just go
and grab it, bring it in, and be off to
the races and not have to spend time
working out all the edge cases, working
out all the carveouts, debugging what's
going on inside of some custom code. you
know, there's an ecosystem, a rich
ecosystem out there for around a lot of
these projects, including Serbos that,
you know, is making this the offering
better without you having to dedicate
time, effort, and engineering resource
inside of your own business to go and
build things. Yeah, edge cases excluded.
I would take a serious look at like do
we really need to be spending our time
on this and we're past the zero interest
rate phenomena of the early 2020s and
we're now in a world where we need to be
really looking at are we delivering the
right value to our customers and are we
delivering what our customers need and
are we putting our all of our effort
focusing on that rather than these other
external things that we just pick up off
the shelf and use. You want to add
anything to it? I mean the question is
Alex touched upon a important point like
you wouldn't build your own database,
you wouldn't build your own software
infrastructure unless it's going to make
your software differentiated than any
other competitors of yours. It it has a
specific need in there. One other state
of software building that doesn't need
authorization but for that same reason
doesn't need also authentication or many
other things many other security
features is when you are actually
building your PC. Not even P, let's call
it P and P. You want to make sure your
technology can solve a problem in the
world, right? And at that point, you're
just very much so focusing on making the
machine work to solve the problem. But
the moment you need to take that
solution and actually now make it
available to your end user, to your
customers, that's the moment where
authentication and authorization and
everything else is the time you need to
start thinking about it and put those
restrictions in place. Great. So I think
the the next logical question I have is
what are the challenges that one would
face if you had an external or decoupled
authorization? Maybe can you state like
three hard challenges? So I guess
firstly it's worth kind of explaining
what decoupled or externalized
authorization is. If you think of
authorization logic, if you were to just
do something quick, you would probably
end up in a situation where in your
codebase, you would have like an if
statement somewhere or a case switch
statement that says if user ro equals
admin, let this request go through. If
user role equals manager, only you allow
this request under XY Z. Sorry. And for
those small applications, you know,
that's perfectly fine. Get you where you
need to get to. Prove the value. Cool.
Move on. But as your application grows,
particularly if your application is
starting to made of lots of services and
those services might be in different
languages. Anytime you need to evolve or
change or update that authorization
logic, which spoilers will happen,
you're going to have to go and touch
that code. And that code is going to get
more and more fragile as you add more
complexity to it. And there's going to
be more places you need to update logic.
And whenever the business requirement
changes, you're going to have to take
that written juror or whatever, and
convert that into application code. And
that application code might actually
need to be in Go, might be in Java,
might be in .NET, depending on what your
services are. and then you're going to
have to go touch and redeploy all your
applications etc. The other side of it
is from a business awareness
perspective, you know, we as developers
are happy to write code all day, but
those that actually define the
requirements for authorization are more
on the business side of things and maybe
in a security team may not even know
code. And if they need to actually go
and look and understand how some logic
was implemented, they probably can't
because they don't know Java, they don't
know Go, they don't know XY Z language.
So the advantages of externalized
authorization is you're externalizing,
funnily enough, all that logic out into
a standalone service or standalone
component in your application stack. And
that component has in it the
authorization logic. And now because
it's just another service inside of your
setup, your authorization logic can be
defined in something that's maybe a bit
more easier for someone that isn't a
developer to understand. So it could be
policy files. We talking about policy
based access control. could be you know
lookup tables or data stores if you're
using one of the other models and that's
a central source of truth that's a
central one place where all that logic
is defined it could be version
controlled it could be tested it could
be fully audited etc and then in each
part of your application architecture
where you want to actually then check
permissions rather than having all that
logic hardcoded in there you're
essentially just calling out to that
authorization service and will you
simply say okay here's this request
here's the user here's the resource and
here's the action they're trying to do
and then that gets sent over to that
authorization service which then
evaluates his policies and returns back
a allow and deny. So that you no longer
need that if else case switch star logic
littered across your codebase. It's now
a simple if statement. If the
authorization service says allow, do the
action. If not, return some sort of
error. And that really gives you two big
benefits. One is whenever you want to
change your authorization logic, there's
a one place you could do it. You update
it once, you make sure tests all work,
etc., etc. push out that policy change
and then all your different parts of
your application architecture that do
authorization are now behaving based
upon the new logic without you having to
touch your application code. And
secondly, and for regulated businesses
or high compliance environments, this is
a really key one because there is a
single component in your stack that is
doing all the authorization checks,
there's a single point where you can
capture an audit log of every decision
and every action that was made inside of
your application. That covers a single
point and that's going to be consistent.
it's going to be well structured. You're
not having to cobble together logs from
different application services etc. And
that gets you into a world where this
externalized or decoupled authorization
model gives you kind of lots of
advantages around that audibility,
visibility and scalability ultimately to
get authorization logic across your
application. And on the back of that, if
we want to focus on the hard parts of
migrating onto this would be one for
existing pieces of software, you need to
now figure out where you're doing all
these checks and actually replace them
rather than a business logic in there.
Replace them with a API call or like
local library call to seros or to your
authorization check system. And the
bigger I wouldn't call it a challenge
but it's the effort that's required from
this is also looking at your software
and trying to centralize or try to
define the authorization requirements of
your system. How many roles do you have
and what does that mean when you have
that role? Which components can that
role access? Which actions can they do
under what circumstances? coming up with
that meta understanding of your
authorization and turning that and then
once you understand it, writing that
into a policy takes minutes to maybe a
couple of hours. But it's actually the
understanding your system and being able
to nail down your authorization
requirements is the harder part of the
process. So what about the challenges
now that the authorization is kind of
moved out to another place? Then it
almost feels like you're losing a bit of
control, right? if you're used to having
it in your code. I mean, of course, it's
great because it's one less check to do,
but the thing is, what are the
challenges if you were outside? Would
there be like a latency challenge or
other things if you have to go to some
other place to pick up the decision to
allow something? As with kind of
everything with Z software architecture,
there's a compromise you need to make.
And one of the things that you do run
into once you start externalizing
authorization is you are going to put
another blocking call essentially in
your request pipeline. Now depending on
what authorization solution you're using
and whether it's a stateful or a
stateless system will very much depend
on what that deployment looks like. What
we always say to seros users is make
sure you run seros as close to your
application as possible. So I'm sure
many are familiar with like cubernetes.
The way we recommend deploying servos in
that environment is you run a seroscar
in every one of your application pods
that needs to do authorization checks.
So you basically bypassing as much as
the network as possible. It's just a
local call at that point. And then your
authorization layer itself should be
smart enough to figure out how to
distribute policies in a sensible,
scalable, consistent way across your
architecture. And so actual the runtime
checks, the lookups and then the
permission checks are being done are
literally just talking locally inside of
its own pod to get a decision. And
there's lots of things you can do around
like choice of APIs, whether you use GPC
or HTTP, all these sort of decisions you
can make and options that you should be
considering when you're doing a
deployment of something like this. But
the biggest one that does need some
thought is your deployment to reduce
things like latency and number of hops
involved. You know, do you start doing
things at the gateway level? Do you
start thinking down at the service
level? Do you use authorization just to
populate your claims in your token?
There's other approaches you could do
still using an authorization service
that is managed centrally to get to
where you need from a security posture
point of view but also a performance and
an SLO perspective as side of your
system. Okay. Uh so brings us then to
like Serbos which is a policy based
access control. So what inspired the
creation of Serbos and what's the gap in
the market that you were trying to fill?
What inspired the creation was the fact
that you know earlier Alex was talking
about this our previous lives we had to
I think collectively within our founding
team we had to build this authorization
build or rebuild or improve 10 times and
every single time we've done it we've
been always complaining about why are we
still building this contributes zero
differentiating features to our product
yet it was something that we had to
actually go and build and at the time
looking at the solution in the market.
None of those things actually really
addressed the challenges that we had. So
the gap in the market that we've seen
was there wasn't a good decoupled or
let's not call it decoupled necessarily.
So authorization solution that we could
have easily implemented and moved on
with our lives. And funny enough as we
were starting Serbos that was a pretty
much the same time where many other
authorization decoupled authorization or
externalized authorization providers
also started the same thing which kind
of told us okay the market is now ready
for this. This is the right time to do
it. And our goal was always making life
easier for software developers so they
can actually just purely focus on what
they want to build, what they need to
build rather than having to reinvent the
wheel when it comes to security. And as
we all know, nobody really likes to
reinvent the security wheel because it's
hard. It has a lot of loopholes. It has
a lot of gotchas. And we wanted to
provide developers something robust and
safe, secure and fast enough so that
they could have one less worry as they
were building the product they were
building. You talked about Serbos the
primary users being developers but are
you focused on startups or enterprises
or what are the primary users of Serbos?
So the users we see kind of will vary
based upon the type of organization.
Serless at its core is an open-source
policy decision point. It's an open
source project. Ready to go. Grab off
GitHub, go and enjoy it. Patch two
license. But the requirements of
authorization and who's involved with
authorization will very much depend on,
you know, what your business is doing.
What we see is startups earlier on as
said earlier, you kind of get going and
prove the value with something quite
simple and then you might mature in
terms using something that's like
externalized authorization later on. But
if you're working in a a regulated
industry, you know, finance, medical
technology, insurance, those kind of
industries, even as a startup, you're
going to have those much stricter
requirements around authorization
earlier on. And in those type of
businesses, the requirement isn't coming
from a developer who's just trying to,
you know, get something implemented
quickly and may seros the requirements
now actually literally coming from the
whole value of the business. Being say a
fintech, you have strict access control
requirements you have to implement if
you're going to be a regulated business.
So you're now getting those requirements
from the security team, the product
team, the compliance team inside of the
company and you'll end up implementing a
standardized externalized stateless hope
authorization system much earlier on in
the life cycle of your business. In
terms of who's actually involved
authorization, you know, we've been
talking about developers a lot and
ultimately they're the ones that going
to have to write the code. Like there
are the stakeholders here. You have a
DevOps or a platform team who will
actually go and deploy the authorization
system inside of your environments
inside of your clusters. You'll have
maybe a security compliance team that
are doing the regular order reviews of
your policies and running audit checks
etc. If you're as a business you're
getting subject data access requests
from users and you need to be able to
pull out what they did inside of a
system that be coming from a different
part of the team. There's also teams you
may not necessarily think of you know
your customer support team who might be
handling support tickets about why can't
I access the system might need some
insight into the authorization logic
behind it. Even on like the sales team
if you're trying to you know sell
software to the world and they'll come
to you saying like we got this customer
they really want to use our system but
they have very fine grain authorization
requirements or permission requirements
just due to the nature of their business
or their organizational structure. So
there's actually a lot of different
parts of a company and roles inside of a
company that will have some input and
authorization and as Emry said earlier
the hardest part is actually getting one
to agree on what the requirements are
and then going off and doing the
implementation. Now, one more thing to
add into there is, you know, you might
have your standard software. You might
have just four roles and that might
actually work, but then you might go
sign up a very large customer where they
have 5,000 internal users and those four
roles aren't enough, right? For that
customer, you need 10 different roles
with regions, etc., various other things
or 20, 50. Then you might go sign up
another enterprise customer which has a
different internal structure than the
previous one. And so they want their
roles to be structured differently. So
servos actually in the in that world
allows you to be able to customize your
roles and permissions on a per tenant
basis. So suddenly we go away from one
sizefits-all model where you know the
product manager of the original product
has to think very hard you know how to
get common roles working for all their
customers. Suddenly we give them a world
where every customer can have their own
structure within their software.
Whether you're building software,
leading teams, or shaping product
strategy, legal elements matter. Penary
Law's software design, risk regulation,
and innovation institute is a 4-day
in-person program for tech
professionals. Learn to spot issues like
privacy, AI liability, and compliance
early so you can build smarter and
reduce risk. No law degree required,
just practical insight. Visit
law.upen.edu/software to register.
That's
law.upen.edu/software. Use promo code
software for $50
[Music]
off. So, one of the things when I looked
at the open source git repo and I was
also looking at the open policy agent
cuz we had a show on that as well. How
does seros differ from opa? Yeah, so
Oprah open policy agent is a it's a
great CNCF project. It's heavily adopted
on infrastructure components. So
Kubernetes for example uses Oprah inside
of it as well. And when we started
building Serbos, we looked at kind of
what Opra was doing. We looked at you
know Rio it is language as well and kind
of saw like this is the right idea in
terms of externalizing and taking a
policy based approach to things. But
where we saw there was a bit of a gap is
really focusing on this application
layer permissions. there's a whole set
of things you kind of disregard at that
level. There's a whole set of
capabilities you need on top. And so
when we kind of looked at it, we sort of
went, okay, policy based having a way of
declaring your logic in a version
control tested way of doing things is,
you know, the right idea. But we really
wanted to simplify things down for that
application permission use case, that
kind of multi-tenency application use
case and making sure in that level you
do have much more involvement from
security, from product, from sales, from
customer support. So how can we bring
that kind of same experience but in a
way that those team and those different
parts of the organization can actually
be more involved with authorization. And
the key thing we did there was the
actual policy language itself. So seros
uses YAML. There's no extra language to
learn. Um it's very passible andable.
You can kind of
scly what's going on. The way we
structure things around here are your
resource policies. There's one per
different resource type in your
application. And the way you can say
okay here's a variant for particular
customer XY Z. there's a very clear and
differentiated way of um explaining and
defining the custom rules for that
particular user as well. So looked at
Opra as a great project. We kind of took
our our interpretation of that and
applied our application level permission
lens on top and that's kind of got to
where we are are today and four years
later nearly services being used by well
you see the GitHub stats tens of
thousands of deployments and GitHub
stars and such of our solution out there
in the world and it's meeting this
requirement of this application level
permissions. One thing to add on top of
it is you know OPA is great. OPA is
built for everything. OPA is a very
general purpose one. When we built
servos for just the application layer,
we were able to reduce the footprint a
lot and we were also able to reduce the
response time a lot because you know we
don't have to handle a lot of those
things. So as a result, Serbos is a very
minimal uh deployment when you look at
the CPU requirements and memory of the
application that that it needs from an
application which makes it a great
companion because it almost exerts zero
extra load on your systems and it gives
you this super flexibility in a much
faster response time. That's a very good
distinction that you made of for
infrastructure OPA and then also maybe
general purpose for a lot of things that
OPA uses and this is more for the
application level authorization that we
have. Can you give us a little bit of
how it works under the hood? So I've got
a YAML file and I can fill that in with
all my permissions for a particular
project. Then what happens? Yeah, so you
go through that policy definition
process. So working with the different
stakeholders inside of your business or
on your application, defining your
different resources, the different
actions, the conditions under which they
should be allowed or not. We always
recommend users then go through the
additional step of writing tests against
those. So as well as writing your
policies with servos, you can then give
example fixtures. Here's some example
users. Here's some example resources.
And then define, you know, under which
condition or which action should be
allowed or denied for each of those. And
so you have a test suite. And then we
take a very githops style approach to
actually deployment. So we recommend you
go and check those into a GitHub repo.
Um you go and wire up CI be it something
you run yourself or you use Serbos Hub
which is one of our offerings and now
you have policies that you know are good
and valid and ready to go. For the
deployment side of things you then need
to go and run Serbos the policy decision
point that the container inside of your
infrastructure somewhere. And like I was
saying earlier our recommended approach
is to make sure that service is running
as close to your application deployments
as possible. You know we keep saying the
word stateless and what we're saying in
this context is servos itself doesn't
require a database or a data store or
anything like that to hold users or
resources etc. Serbos is purely
evaluating requests based upon the
context that's passed of it from the
application layer and that stateless
architecture means you can put seros
everywhere. You can put it inside of
every pod and on every cluster in every
deployment and you can have ser spread
out and running everywhere to ensure
that every service has a local version
of the policies to evaluate against. So
you go and deploy your serless instances
is now running inside of your
environment and then the final step is
updating your application code to
actually call that seros instance. So we
have SDKs and APIs available pretty much
every language and framework now and you
do that one type process to update the
application code and call that seros
instance. So that seros instance when
you deploy you can you tell it where to
get its policy files from and we support
a git repo we support a cloud storage
bucket we support just files on disk and
we also support seros hub which is our
managed control plane. So that is a
synchronization layer and CI pipeline
that pulls the policies down as well.
But ultimately those YAML files end up
compiled, tested and distributed out to
your environments and that local policy
decision point running alongside your
application. You simply say here's a
user trying to do this action on this
resource. It evaluates the current
policies, comes up with the decision,
creates an audit log of that decision
and then returns it back to your
application. So it's actually a very
very simple interface by design. There's
essentially one API in seros with a
secondary one for a data filtering use
case where you say user action resource
it goes yes or no that's all you have to
kind of worry about from an
implementation perspective and then all
the smarts and all the rules engine is
all part of the open source project that
you get by pulling seros down into your
architecture you also have like an audit
log is that what you say for every
action so it'll be running sort of
locally and then it gets synced to some
master yeah so every instance of your
policy decision points of your servers
container and generates it order log and
then you have a configurable option of
where you want to send it. If you just
want to use the open source project, you
can have it just log to standard out and
then have your existing logging
infrastructure pick it up and you can
tell it to go right off to a cafka topic
either if you want. Also, you know, we a
very common setup we see is users are
running, you know, the typical low-key
graphano type setup. So that will go
pick up the logs and send them off or
use something like fluentd and those
kind of tools. We also have a managed
log collection system as part of service
hub which gives you a nice UI for
delving into your authorization logs.
And the one thing I will say is audit
logs are kind of one of the superpowers
and also like a bit of a side benefit of
externalizing authorization not just
with seros generally. You know your
application logs are going to be
spitting out all sorts. You'll have you
know stack traces and memory dumps and
all sorts going on there and you're
going to have a very large volume of
data but authorization logs. These audit
decision logs are a kind of a different
type of log that you do need to keep and
you want to have more than a three-month
retention on. You might want to have a
threeyear retention on because of you
know compliance reasons. So being able
to send those specifically to a
destination that is a goes to an
environment that gives tools to your
security team to your compliance team to
your application developers to debug or
access control logic is a real advantage
and and one of the things you just kind
of get for free for using externalized
authorization approach. And that order
log will tell you at this time this user
tried to do this action on this resource
and it was allowed or denied by this
particular version of this particular
policy. And so you get that very
granular insight of what's going on
inside of your system without having to
necessarily dig through your actual
application level logs. Absolutely. I
can see a use case for that. Yeah,
that's a lot of digging that you need to
do. Oh yeah. So thinking about like
where I work at uh sometimes we also
have this case where like if you were
auditing a database there's always you
know you have to decide on what to audit
right every action what should you audit
because again the logs can be huge do
you have to have a similar consideration
with your authorization logs or is that
a bit more leaner yeah so the logs
themselves are a bit leaner because
you're purely just capturing the
decision you're not capturing you know
the whole request context you're not
capturing the whole request pipeline etc
and actually for authorization logs.
Particularly for regulated industries
where you must maintain a log of x
number of years, you do need every
single decision captured because now
you're dealing with the actual actions
of individual customers or users or
subscribers inside of your system and
you need to be able to pull that out and
essentially replay exactly what that
person did. Particularly if you go to a
kind of a subject access request type
environment or you got a suspected
breach identity, you need to be able to
go and fetch that. So your security logs
are a different type of log concern than
kind of the application side of things.
In the regulated industries, it's not
only enough to know who did what and
whether they were allowed to do or so,
but why why were they allowed to do that
and why they weren't. So ultimately
there's that custody chain of not only
what they did, but what that had in the
policies or who changed the policy that
allowed that person to be able to do
something. So they need to be able to
also you know trace it all the way to
the policy and who updated that policy.
At the end of the day let's not call it
fingerpointing but they you know they
want to understand if there's an
incident you want to understand the full
reason behind it and servos allows you
to do that as well because it not only
all the decisions are logged all the
policies and all the all the different
versions of the policies are logged and
with with their entire commit log. So
you can actually figure out you know
what in your organization actually
caused this incident to happen so that
you can actually prevent it next time
properly. Thanks for that. I think that
was a very good discussion we had and I
had a question on the stateless
authorization. How does that work like
so do you work with standards like say
JWT tokens or oath open ID like and how
does it get the context? Yeah. So again
stateless authorization versus stateful
authorization in the stateless model the
authorization layer doesn't maintain any
data store of users or resources versus
the stateful model which would have like
a replica of all your data. So the onus
is on the refer is the policy
enforcement point the component which is
going to do the check to see whether an
authorization should be an action should
be allowed or not. it the onus is on
that component to send the state so who
the user is what the resources and other
context in the request as it happens in
order for the policy engine to evaluate
and come back with a decision. So how
you transfer that data typically it's
just a big JSON object of here's all the
details you need but using standards
like JDTS O2 tokens those sort of things
kind of smooth that journey out so in
the case of seros you can you know fill
in the data yourself or your application
can or you can just go and fill or pass
on the JT directly to seros and then
seros itself can actually go and verify
that token if you can provide the key
set and then the contents that token is
made available inside of the policy and
for the what we refer to as the
principle or the user components of
that. There are, you know, defined
standards for it. You know, the O2 work
and and JBC tokens being the obvious one
there for the actual resources is a bit
more free form because it's down to what
your application data model is. So,
there isn't a standard to point to for
that. But where there is a relevant
standard, those are adopted and can then
be used inside of Servos as well. And
just on the topic of standards more
generally, there is an ongoing effort of
which servos is part of under the open
ID foundation called the orzen working
group which we're active contributors of
around standardizing the API interface
between applications and policy decision
points or authorization services like
Serbos. The first specification has been
published that's out there and is being
now adopted and we're particularly
interested getting more application
implementers to kind of come on board
and work through getting the oren
standard implemented inside of their
application layers of which then you can
then go and plug in any policy decision
point like servos interchangeably into
your different systems in your
applications. Just to kind of build up
on that, for the decisions to happen
where you rely on an external source,
what are they like for like when you're
doing a enforcement of a policy, then
you would you go to a database or API or
is that what you're saying is
configurable? So, we have a pretty
strict line on what seros itself or
policy decision point should do inside
of the system. And one of the things we
really design for is predictability
inside of how your policy decision point
will behave. So Serbos is fully
stateless in the sense that it doesn't
store state but it also won't call out
and go and fetch state from other parts
of your systems. You know my background
as well as Emry is from building very
high throughput low latency data
processing systems. You know billions
and billions of requests a day is the
kind of typical day for us in our
previous lives. And so we've made kind
of every mistake possible when it comes
to eventual consistency and scalability
and thundering herd problems and all
that sort of stuff. And one of the
things we decided very early on when
when defining servos and specifying
servos is servos itself when it's
running once it's got its policies in
there it would not do anything else on
your system. It is down to the cooling
application to pass all the state
through there and the primary driver to
that is many orders of layers of
management and process involved etc
behind someone may make a very small
change to a policy and if that policy
decision point had the ability to go and
fetch state from across your
architecture. one small change in a
policy somewhere upstream once it hits
your production environment, that small
change could actually result in some
massively unexpected load to some other
part of your architecture because that
policy now needs to go and fetch some
new data point about you from some other
system which doesn't normally get any
traffic. You're now going to push this
change out and now suddenly that system
is not scaled. It's not ready. You're
now going to add this massive latency or
even just request failures because it
can't handle the load to your system. So
we made that call early on from like I
said being burnt in previous lives to
make sure that seros is extremely
predictable in what it will do and what
load and performance characteristics it
will have across your architecture and
it will never be in a position where it
can start putting unexpected load and
and traffic onto other parts of your
system. So where do you store policies
in a stateless decoupled framework and
if something changes uh how do you do
this policy reloading without uh
disrupting a service in a distributed
environment? Yeah. Hot reloading and
such. Yeah. Yeah. Absolutely. So in the
distributed environments there's
obviously the challenge is how do you
get those policy files down to those
different instances that deployed
potentially hundreds if not thousands in
some cases across your architecture. So
the way this works is you store your
policy centrally. As I mentioned
earlier, they could be a GitHub repo, it
could be in a storage bucket, it could
be an asset stored somewhere inside of
your stack. And then each of those seros
instances in the open source project,
you configure it to say go and get the
policies from this location. And that is
a pool model. So each of those servos
instances will go and check on some
regular configurable basis from a git
repo or from an S3 bucket or wherever
you're storing your policies and will
pull those policies down and swap them
hot swap them in memory if they're valid
to go and start evaluating based on it.
Now for those of you that have dealt
with these kind of problems before you
kind of immediately run into the problem
of well if I've got 100 serverless
instances running and each of them is
taking 10-second intervals to check for
updates it's going to take up to 10
seconds let's say for a policy change to
apply. you know that may be okay for
your scenario or it may actually be a
bit of a problem depending how fast
moving your policies are. So it's part
of serus hub which is our management
control plane that sits on top of the
open source project. We flip that model
around and it becomes much more of a
push model and so we can actually
coordinate and synchronize the roll out
of policy updates across the entire
fleet without you having to kind of
worry about anything like that. So the
policies are still stored in a central
location a git repo or storage bucket
etc. But the compilation and
distribution on those policy updates is
now coordinated via the control plane
and that is seros hub. I guess the next
question I have is you talked a little
bit about testing that's offered as a
part of subos like so how do you test
and validate policies do you have like
some examples that you can talk about
like how do you validate like a new
policy? Yeah certainly so there's a
validation step and there's a a testing
step. So first off because seros we use
you know mentioned previous earlier um
YAML as our format for actually running
policies there's a strict schema for
that we publish those schemas publicly
so your you know your VS code your
editor of choice um whatever you may be
using these days will light up and give
you validation of the actual structure
of the policies themselves autocomplete
all that sort of fun stuff as the kind
of the first step and then seros itself
has this testy framework built in as
well so you can define your policy file
structure may be valid but then you want
to make sure it's logically valid as
well. So you define those test cases,
example users, example resources,
expected actions and then as part of the
the open source CLI tool, it goes
through that firstly validate the
structure and then also run all the
tests. Make sure that the expected
outcomes are as they should be similar
with any sort of test-driven type
development and those same tests can
then be running in run in your CI
pipeline. be it when you set up yourself
say GitHub actions we publish a GitHub
action for that or as part of more of a
managed control plane offering like
service hub I also wanted to ask you one
more question everybody's now at the
time where they're trying to build their
own chat bots or LLMs and you know those
models so when you do this authorization
I feel like a lot of the good practices
that we got on say these you know web
application based projects OASP and all
of that we had a lot of checks that were
there and it's important to do but with
the AI and ML chat box some of them are
lost. But do you think is it a different
type of framework that has to be applied
to those kind of applications or do we
use the same principles? Yes and no is
the answer. When it comes to you know
software engineering it's it's never a
pure yes or a pure no. So if you look
back at software development, we've
spent the last 40 years in trying to
secure the back end and the front end
and the communication in between them,
right? And now with the AI being so
advanced and chatbot technology has been
around and when those two married
suddenly we have now a third interface
where you know the AI can actually have
access to your data and it's actually
even potentially bypassing your back end
and it's having you know unrestricted
access to your data to be able to train
the models and then it can actually get
also the same models LLM models and same
you know rag architecture and AI can
give you the answer straight out right
and it does bypassing your entire back
end and front end security that you've
actually built in there. A classic
example of this is you can think about
any analytics system or like any HR
system where there's an AI chatbot on
top right it's leaking data because you
know if a CEO asks for you know what's
the current payroll he should get an
answer of inclusive of the entire
company's information but if a regional
VP asks hey what's the payroll it
shouldn't actually give the same answer
it should only give the answer for that
given region etc. So we need to now
start securing these AI chat bots, AI
agents with the limitations of the user.
And in order to be able to do that, we
need to be able to actually filter the
data that comes into these AI models and
filter the data that actually comes out
of it. and Serbos with its you know data
filtering authorization aware data
filtering capability something that Alex
talked about earlier which is the query
planning and being able to actually
filter the data based on what you should
have access on gives possibility to the
AI agents to be able to only return a
subset of data rather than entirety of
it. So there is a use case for the AI
agents to be able to use this
authorization logic when as the data is
passing through it. Great. Because I was
just thinking when you're talking that
even about this that Chevy chatbot,
right? I think they had this case where
it was just opened without any controls
and I think finally I think the chatbot
they could uh they had to like give them
a Chevy for a $1 or something like that
because the person had like prompt
engineer. There are lots of examples of
this, right? In terms of there are, you
know, some in airlines, there be some
cheap tickets and refunds being given.
At the end of the day, we need to
actually inspect each one of these
things that the LLM models is returning
as a response and turn them into
potential API calls and be able to check
if the user is actually allowed to do
certain things. Okay. So then in that
case also like a policy decision point
should be built on top of those chat
bots is what I'm saying. So that's lots
of be absolutely. So seros policy
decision point has actually two major
API. One API is very specific question.
Can this user do this action to this or
can this you know subject or principle
or user whatever we want to call it do
this action to this resource. It's a
very deterministic question yes or no.
And then the second question is what
resources can this user do this action
on? And being able to actually filter
that being able to give that gives you
the ends ability to be able to filter
your data as it's coming out of a
database to those only those records
that the user has access to. Great. So
the last question I want to ask you both
is do you see opportunities for say AI
or ML to complement stateless
frameworks? I was uh reading this paper
a few days back on adaptive
authorization and anomaly detection. Is
that something that you think will be
the future or is it already being done
at Servos here or other places? Yeah, so
there's lots of places that I think
makes sense to use this kind of new
world. There's also a couple places
where I think you definitely do not want
some AI model meddling it. And the
places where I think it makes sense is
at the start of the process when you're
trying to take those business
requirements and convert them to policy.
I think that's a really interesting area
for innovation and you can ask ask Chad
Gyt or Claude at the moment here my
requirements give me a service policy
and they actually most of them will and
it will come out with a pretty good
policy these days so which is kind of
nice so it's clearly read all our
documentation etc and at the other end
of it which is once you got that audit
log of all the decisions being made you
got that log stream that's another area
where you can start doing things like
anomaly detection and understanding kind
of what's going on and use these new
tools to you know help you find the
signal from the noise so I think Those
are two ripe areas for opportunity.
Where I have I'm strongly think today at
least AI should not be involved is right
in the middle where the actual
decisioning process happens.
Authorization is rules. It is business
requirements. It is compliance needs. It
is regulatory hurdles that must be met
and that needs to be certain to behave
in a certain way. You don't want to be
worried about what the temperature of
the model that's deciding your
authorization logic should be. You need
to make sure that that middle point, the
actual com the component, the rules
engine, the evaluation engine is always
going to give you the right answer every
single time. And that is where good
code, efficient code, you know, call it
uh handwritten artisal code if you want
in the middle should be the one driving
the system. But certainly the this new
world of tools could really help us on
the both the authoring and the
understanding side of things. The
enforcement needs to be deterministic
and you cannot afford to hallucinate
even once because that one instance may
cause a disaster. That's a nice way to
end the show. It has to be deterministic
the policy enforcement. Great. Uh so
what's a good place to reach you if
somebody wanted to in cyerspace like our
listeners Alex and Emra? Would it be
LinkedIn, Twitter or X or anywhere else?
Absolutely. So our website is
servos.dev. All of our resources, all of
our product and all of our documentation
can be found there. If you want to reach
us or our teams, we have a Slack
community that we are pretty responsive
on and you know, we want to help
developers adopt externalized
authorization as much as they can. And
then if you want to reach out to me
individually, Emra Baran on LinkedIn and
Emry on Twitter X. Yeah. And I'm Alex
Liv on LinkedIn and Alex Livy on
Twitter. Great. I'll make sure to add
that to the show notes. This has been a
great show. Thanks for coming. This is
Priyanka Ragin for Software Engineering
Radio. Thanks for listening.
Thanks for listening to SE Radio, an
educational program brought to you by it
e software magazine. For more about the
podcast, including other episodes, visit
our website at se-radio.net.
To provide feedback, you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn, Facebook, Twitter, or
through our Slack channel at
seradio.slack.com. You can also email us
at
teamse-radio.net. This and all other
episodes of SE Radio is licensed under
creative common license 2.5. Thanks for
listening.